Mosab Ibrahim

United Kingdom



mosab.a.ibrahim@gmail.com



+44 741 565 4481



linkedin.com/in/mosab

Summary

A resourceful and passionate Software & Systems Engineer with almost two decades of experience in designing, developing, operating and maintaining software systems at various scales, solving problems in different industries & domains.

I am especially passionate about Developing Large-scale Systems, Linux, Systems Programming, Distributed Systems, and Automation at Scale, as well as Free Software and Open-source Software.

Currently working in the capacity of a Production Engineer at Facebook/Meta.

Previously I worked on improving the availability, scalability, performance and reliability of Twitter's production services, in a quest to give everyone the power to create and share ideas and information instantly without barriers, as well as other great companies like GoCardless, Levelset, Wuzzuf, Inmobly, 20@, and more!

Experience

Production Engineer

Meta

Mar 2022 - Present (1 month +)

Senior Site Reliability Engineer

Twitter

May 2020 - Mar 2022 (1 year 11 months)

c Site Reliability Engineer

GoCardless

Mar 2019 - May 2020 (1 year 3 months)

Software Engineer

Nov 2017 - Mar 2019 (1 year 5 months)

- Develop, deploy, & maintain customer-facing microservices (Java/PHP) handling over billion requests/day.
- Create, and maintain infrastructure as code for new and legacy systems/microservices.
- Own services uptime, and perform systems troubleshooting & debugging.

Software Development Technical Lead

Levelset

Jan 2017 - Sep 2017 (9 months)

- Leading a team designing & developing an internal platform for data verification and research process.

- Migrating zlien.com's platform to a microservices based architecture.
- Designing & building zlien's API that ingests 100K+ transactions every week from our customers' systems.
- Designing & and building various products targeting new customer segments.
- Reduced release time from an average of 1-2 days, to an average of 3-7 minutes by automating the process.
- Turned the few downtimes a week into 99.9% uptime of the platform for the past 4 years.
- Administrating Git source repositories, defining branching strategies and tutoring the engineering teams about it.

Senior Software Engineer, DevOps

Levelset

Mar 2013 - Jan 2017 (3 years 11 months)

- Designing and implementing the application's architecture and infrastructure.
- Developing new features for our SaaS platform.
- Designing and implementing the platform's APIs, and helping with the on-boarding and supporting of our clients to use our APIs.
- Develop infrastructure and tools for system monitoring, performance measurements, and fully automated deployments
- Working closely with developers and other staff to solve operational issues with our services, tools and apps.
- Working with the team to design and build scalable systems that support high traffic web services.

Senior Software Engineer

inmobly

Jan 2012 - May 2012 (5 months)

Developing and maintaining server side stacks using C++, Python, MySQL, PHP, Linux and any necessary technology to serve as the API consumed by the company's mobile and tablet applications.

Bluwo Technical Consultant

Bluw i Limited

Jun 2011 - Sep 2011 (4 months)

- Developing an on-going project Drupal project for a client from scratch.
- Providing PHP and Drupal consultation for other projects at the company.
- Implementing scrum software management process alongside with the technical manager.
- Interacting with the client to gather requirements and provide progres updates.

Senior PHP Developer

BasharSoft

Apr 2010 - Apr 2011 (1 year 1 month)

- Architect, design, and implement wuzzuf.net platform with the team.
- Co-leading the development team along with the company's CTO.
- Manage, monitor and maintain the online production servers for wuzzuf.net platform.
- Take lead role along with the CTO in applying agile practices and techniques.
- Collaborate with team members to enhance the platform's user experience.

Software Engineer

Arabia Inform

Nov 2009 - Apr 2010 (6 months)

Migrated some internal tooling projects from proprietary suites to open source software.

Software Engineer

Oct 2008 - Nov 2009 (1 year 2 months)

- Building websites hosted on Amazon Web Services that acted as gateways routing orders and information to and from a complicated proprietary printing system hosted on-premise at the client's printing pipelines.
- Interacting with the client to gather requirements and provide progress updates.

PHP Developer & Linux Server Administrator

Media International

Jan 2007 - Sep 2008 (1 year 9 months)

- Developing customized web applications for our clients mainly using Drupal and Joomla, but sometimes with other tools as well.
- Designing and executing data migration projects for some of our clients from legacy systems to solutions provided by our team.
- Surveying, and reviewing tools for internal use by our team.
- Load balancing linux web servers and implementing MySQL replication and file synchronization solutions.
- Monitoring the servers, resolving production issues, and maintaining uptime.

PHP Developer

20at.com

Jan 2004 - Dec 2006 (3 years)

- Developing a new content management solution (CMS) from scratch to meet the editorial and business requirements
- Designing and executing data migration plan from the legacy version of the website to the newly developed system.
- Maintaining the online website codebase, and applying bug and security fixes.
- Developing new features and sub-portals in reaction to business needs and special current events (elections, world cup, uprisings, etc).

Education



Cairo University

Dropout, Computer Engineering 2002 - 2007



Ahmed Bahgat High school

High school, General Studies 1999 - 2002

Skills

Linux • Python • PHP • Web Services • Web Development • Software Engineering • OOP • Cloud Computing • C • java